Guide to the Thomas Irwin Emerson Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Thomas Irwin Emerson papers
1933-1988
1946-1976
MS 1622
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
42
The papers consist of correspondence, writings, course material, legal documents, and printed material that document Thomas Emerson's career as a lawyer and law professor. The papers emphasize Emerson's teaching, writing, and organizational activities during his career at the Yale Law School from 1946 to 1976.
Emerson, Thomas I. (Thomas Irwin), 1907-1991
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the Estate of Thomas Irwin Emerson, 1991-1992.
Arrangement
Arranged in four series: I. Correspondence and Subject Files, 1933-1988. II. Personal Papers, 1937-1987. III. Writings, 1947-1987. IV. Course Materials, 1946-1983.
Scope and Contents
The papers document the career of Thomas Emerson, primarily during his time as a professor at the Yale Law School from 1946 to 1976. Correspondence runs throughout the papers but is concentrated in Series I, residing in both the general correspondence section and the subject files. The subject files consist largely of collected material and detail Emerson's involvement in organizations. His activities on behalf of the American Civil Liberties Union, the Connecticut Civil Liberties Union, and the Permanent Commission on the Status of Women are among those most thoroughly documented. The subject files also contain a limited amount of material from the period Emerson spent working for the federal government from 1933 to 1946. The papers include copies of the files the Federal Bureau of Investigation kept on Emerson and large amounts of Emerson's writings and course materials. While his legal career is represented in the papers, legal documentation is not a large part of the collection. Records of Griswold v. Connecticut are present, but not extensive. There is no documentation of Powell v. Alabama or the other "Scottsboro Boys" cases in these papers.
The papers provide a comprehensive view of many of the debates over civil liberties in the United States during the twentieth century. Material within the papers details American society's ongoing struggle to define the boundaries between an individual's rights and government sovereignty in the political, social, and intellectual arenas. Emerson's involvement in the Progressive Party, support of the Equal Rights Amendment, and work on Sweezy v. New Hampshire are well-documented civil liberties issues within the papers, but many others are present in the subject files in Series I. On a more personal note, the Federal Bureau of Investigation files in Series II show how the FBI conducted an investigation of a suspected member of the Communist Party, the scope of the investigation, and the effect it had on the person being investigated. Emerson was one of many people to be investigated in this way by government agencies after World War II.
The Thomas Irwin Emerson Papers were processed as part of a collaborative effort between Manuscripts and Archives and the Yale Law School to document the careers and accomplishments of law school faculty and alumni.
Biographical / Historical
Thomas Irwin Emerson was born on July 12, 1907, in Passaic, New Jersey. He graduated from Yale College in 1928 and from the Yale Law School in 1931. Upon graduation from law school, Emerson worked for two years at the New York law firm of Engelhard, Pollak, Pitcher and Stern. In 1931, he served on the defense team in Powell v. Alabama, the suit that successfully overturned the convictions of the "Scottsboro Boys" and is considered a groundbreaking case in establishing a defendant's right to counsel. Emerson left the law firm in 1933 and went to work for the federal government. He spent thirteen years in Washington, D.C., working for seven government agencies during the period of President Franklin D. Roosevelt's New Deal. He began as assistant counsel for the National Recovery Administration. From there, he went to the National Labor Relations Board, the Social Security Board, the National Labor Relations Board again, the Department of Justice, and the Office of Price Administration. He completed his time as a government employee with assignments as general counsel for the Office of Economic Stabilization and the Office of War Mobilization and Reconversion. His memoirs from this period were published in 1991 in the book Young Lawyer for the New Deal: An Insider's Memoir of the Roosevelt Years. In 1946, Emerson joined the Yale Law School faculty. He taught at the law school until 1976. He was a popular professor among students and taught such courses as Political and Civil Rights, Constitutional Law, and Administrative Process. His publications included over one hundred articles and briefs as well as two highly regarded scholarly works, Political and Civil Rights in the United States with David Haber, first published in 1952, and The System of Freedom of Expression published in 1970.
Throughout his life, Emerson was a passionate civil libertarian. His organizational activity demonstrated the importance he assigned to the protection of civil liberties. He was active in both the American Civil Liberties Union and the New Haven Civil Liberties Council, later called the Connecticut Civil Liberties Union. He served as an advisor to the Civil Liberties Educational Foundation and as a member of the national council for the Emergency Civil Liberties Committee. He fought against repressive government legislation in the National Committee to Abolish the House Committee on Un-American Activities and the National Committee Against Repressive Legislation and opposed the Federal Loyalty Program. Emerson also defended civil liberties in the courtroom. In 1957, he argued and won a case before the Supreme Court, Sweezy v. New Hampshire, that reinforced the right to academic freedom. In the 1960s, he contributed to the effort to secure the release of Morton Sobell, convicted in 1951 of espionage and detained in prison past the duration of his sentence. In recognition of his defense of civil liberties, he received the inaugural American Civil Liberties Union's Medal of Liberty in 1984.
In 1965, Emerson argued before the Supreme Court in Griswold v. Connecticut that the Connecticut state law forbidding the use of contraceptives was unconstitutional. The Supreme Court ruled in his favor and, as part of the decision, recognized a right to privacy under the Constitution for the first time. Legal scholars consider the case the precursor to the Roe v. Wade decision legalizing abortion. He further demonstrated his commitment to women's rights as a member of the Permanent Commission on the Status of Women and the Connecticut Women's Educational and Legal Fund and by campaigning for the passage of the Equal Rights Amendment in the 1970s.
Emerson's organizational affiliations and defense of civil liberties during the reactionary period in the United States after World War II resulted in government surveillance. Copies of records Emerson obtained through a Freedom of Information Act request document the Federal Bureau of Investigation's observance of him between 1941 and 1977. The investigation began as series of background checks for Emerson's various government positions and intensified as a result of his involvement in the National Lawyers Guild, an organization attacked as a Communist front during the 1940s, and his co-authoring of an article in 1948 criticizing the Federal Loyalty Program. The FBI's efforts to connect him with the Communist Party included trying to place him with a Communist cell in Seattle, Washington, a city Emerson had never visited. Emerson steadfastly denied Communist Party membership and the FBI failed in its attempts to prove otherwise.
Thomas Emerson and his first wife, Bertha Paret, had three children: Joan, Robert and Luther. Later, Emerson married Ruth Calvin. Thomas Emerson died June 19, 1991, in New Haven, Connecticut.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Academic freedom; Anti-communist movements -- United States; Birth control -- Law and legislation; Civil rights -- Connecticut; Civil rights -- United States; Freedom of speech -- United States; Internal security -- United States; Law -- Study and teaching; Political rights -- United States; Women -- Legal status, laws, etc.; Women's rights; Emerson, Thomas I. (Thomas Irwin), 1907-1991; Harper, Fowler V. (Fowler Vincent), 1897-1965; United States. Federal Bureau of Investigation; Progressive Party (U.S.: 1948); Yale Law School
- Correspondence and Subject Files, 1933-1988; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  The series includes correspondence and other materials collected or created by Thomas Emerson. It begins with a chronological run of general correspondence, then is arranged alphabetically by subject using headings created by Emerson. Although general correspondence is arranged separately, correspondence relating to a specific subject remains with that subject. The correspondence, both general and subject-specific, is largely routine. Correspondents include statesman Chester Bowles, attorney Catherine Roraback, law professor Catharine MacKinnon, and law professor and president of the American Civil Liberties Union Norman Dorsen.
  In addition to correspondence, materials filed under topical headings include meeting minutes, publications, and news clippings from organizations Emerson participated in or subjects of interest to him. The records on the American Civil Liberties Union, the New Haven Civil Liberties Council, the Connecticut Civil Liberties Union, and the National Committee Against Repressive Legislation chronicle Emerson's activities in defense of civil liberties. The material on the Equal Rights Amendment and the Permanent Commission on the Status of Women reveal his commitment to women's rights. Records from the National Labor Relations Board, the Office of Price Administration, and the Office of War Mobilization and Reconversion document Emerson's career in government service.
  The Progressive Party records provide evidence of Emerson at his most active in an organized political party. The records include an explanation of Emerson's brief entrance into the 1948 Connecticut gubernatorial race and of his resignation from state party leadership a few years later over the national party's position on the Korean War.
  The series also contains records from several legal cases in which Emerson participated. The cases include Griswold v. Connecticut regarding birth control, Sweezy v. New Hampshire regarding academic freedom, and the Sobell case in which Emerson worked for the release from prison of Morton Sobell, convicted in 1951 of espionage. The records include correspondence, notes, and copies of briefs, motions, opinions, and petitions. There is no documentation of Powell v. Alabama or the other "Scottsboro Boys" cases in these papers.
  - General correspondence
    - 1942-1957 May (Box 1, Folder 1 - 11)
    - 1957 June-1967 January (Box 2, Folder 12 - 26)
    - 1967 February-1970 (Box 3, Folder 27 - 42)
    - 1971-1975 (Box 4, Folder 43 - 63)
    - 1976-1980 February (Box 5, Folder 64 - 80)
    - 1980 March-1984 (Box 6, Folder 81 - 96)
    - 1985-1988, undated (Box 7, Folder 97 - 105)
    - Crank mail, 1949-1980 (Box 7, Folder 106 - 108)
  - Abortion
    - General, 1969-1985, undated (Box 7, Folder 109 - 110)
    - Constitutional amendment, 1975-1984, undated (Box 7, Folder 111 - 112)
    - Doe v. Israel, 1973, undated (Box 8, Folder 113)
    - Human life and jurisdiction bills, 1981, undated (Box 8, Folder 114)
  - Academic freedom
    General note
    See also: box 64, 885 - 889
    - General, 1949-1983 (Box 8, Folder 115 - 119)
    - Arons-Lawrence Conference on Socialization in Schools, 1980 (Box 8, Folder 120)
    - California, 1950-1951 (Box 8, Folder 121)
    - Court decisions, 1966-1978, undated (Box 8, Folder 122 - 123)
    - Endangered Rights, 1983, undated (Box 8, Folder 124)
    - Law and Contemporary Problems: Symposium on Academic Freedom, 1963-1965 (Box 8, Folder 125)
    - Leo Koch case, 1961-1963 (Box 9, Folder 126 - 129)
    - Statements of principles, 1966, 1981, undated (Box 9, Folder 130)
    - Staughton Lynd case, 1967 (Box 9, Folder 131)
    - Students, 1962-1977 (Box 9, Folder 132 - 134)
  - Administrative Procedure Act, 1963-1965 (Box 9, Folder 135)
  - Affirmative action, 1976-1983, undated (Box 9, Folder 136 - 137)
  - Affirmative governmental controls, 1968-1970, 1981, undated (Box 9, Folder 138)
  - American Bar Association [report on character evaluation], 1972 (Box 9, Folder 139)
  - American Civil Liberties Union
    - General, 1975-1986 (Box 10, Folder 140 - 141)
    - Civil Liberties Review, 1972-1977 (Box 10, Folder 142)
    - Correspondence, 1952-1968 (Box 10, Folder 143 - 145)
    - Free Speech/Association Committee
      - 1970-1982 June (Box 10, Folder 146 - 151)
      - 1982 July-1985 (Box 11, Folder 152 - 153)
    - Karpatkin Fellowship, 1975-1988 (Box 11, Folder 154)
    - Medal of Liberty Award, 1983-1984 (Box 11, Folder 155)
    - Meeting minutes, 1965 (Box 11, Folder 156)
    - Nominating Committee, 1976-1977 (Box 11, Folder 157)
    - Privacy Committee, 1967-1968, undated (Box 11, Folder 158)
    - Special Committee on Military Free Speech, 1967-1968 (Box 11, Folder 159)
    - Special Committee on Private Pressure Groups, 1973-1981, undated (Box 11, Folder 160)
    - Women's Rights Project, 1976-1978 (Box 11, Folder 161 - 163)
  - American Federation of Teachers, Local 204, 1954-1969 (Box 11, Folder 164)
  - American independent movement, 1966 (Box 11, Folder 165)
  - American Jewish Congress, Commission on Law and Social Action, 1946 (Box 11, Folder 166)
  - Amnesty [for war resisters], 1972-1975, undated (Box 11, Folder 167)
  - Anti-Riot legislation, 1967, undated (Box 11, Folder 168)
  - Aptheker case, 1977-1978 (Box 11, Folder 169 - 170)
  - Association of American Law Schools, Committee on Supreme Court Decisions, 1964-1972 (Box 12, Folder 171)
  - Atomic energy, 1948, undated (Box 12, Folder 172)
  - Bail [committee against preventive detention], 1951-1952, 1969-1970 (Box 12, Folder 173 - 174)
  - Bill of Rights Radio Education Project, 1980-1983 (Box 12, Folder 175)
  - Birth control, 1964-1985, undated (Box 12, Folder 176)
    General
    See also: box 12, folder 182
    See also: box 20, folder 305
    See also: box 27, folder 410
    See also: box 36, folder 524
    See also: box 50, folder 703
    See also: box 63, folders 876 - 877
    See also: box 65, folder 895
    See also: box 67, folder 930
  - Budget [proposed amendment requiring a balanced federal budget]
    - Applications for constitutional convention, 1979-1982, undated (Box 12, Folder 177)
    - Constitutional amendment to balance, 1979-1987, undated (Box 12, Folder 178 - 179)
  - Bujese v. U.S., 1967-1969, undated (Box 12, Folder 180 - 181)
  - Buxton v. Ullman, 1959-1961 (Box 12, Folder 182)
  - Campaign to stop government spying, 1978 (Box 12, Folder 183)
  - Capital punishment, 1966-1975 (Box 12, Folder 184)
  - Censorship
    - American Booksellers Association appeal, 1985 (Box 12, Folder 185)
    - Book banning, 1984 (Box 12, Folder 186)
    - Comic books and other books, 1955-1961 (Box 12, Folder 187)
    - England, Undated (Box 12, Folder 188)
    - Radio and television, 1983-1984 (Box 12, Folder 189)
  - Censorship, obscenity, prior restraint, 1959-1985, undated (Box 13, Folder 190 - 194)
  - Census [special census of metropolitan New Haven], 1967 (Box 13, Folder 195)
  - Center for National Security Studies, 1975-1984 (Box 13, Folder 196 - 197)
  - Center for Research and Education in American Liberties, 1964-1970 (Box 13, Folder 198 - 200)
  - Central Intelligence Agency
    - Budget, 1977 (Box 13, Folder 201)
    - Censorship Oversight Project, 1980, 1982 (Box 13, Folder 202)
  - Church and state
    - General, 1947-1983, undated (Box 14, Folder 203 - 207)
    - Cults, 1981 (Box 14, Folder 208)
    - Education, 1978-1982 (Box 14, Folder 209)
    - School prayer, 1979-1984, undated (Box 14, Folder 210)
    - "Shared time" programs, 1965-1966 (Box 14, Folder 211)
  - Civil disobedience, 1966-1968, undated (Box 14, Folder 212)
  - Civil Liberties Educational Foundation, 1960-1963 (Box 14, Folder 213 - 215)
  - Civil liberties organizations, 1947-1978 (Box 14, Folder 216)
  - Civil rights
    See also: box 50, folder 706
    - General, 1951, 1964, undated (Box 14, Folder 217)
    - Black Panther Party, 1969-1970, undated (Box 14, Folder 218)
    - Commission on Civil Rights, 1958-1962 (Box 14, Folder 219)
    - Federal Civil Rights Act of 1960, 1960, undated (Box 15, Folder 220)
    - Federal registration bill, 1960, undated (Box 15, Folder 221)
    - History, 1951, 1974, undated (Box 15, Folder 222)
    - Proposed legislation, 1962-1968 (Box 15, Folder 223 - 230)
  - Civil Rights Committee [Connecticut Bar Association], 1957-1961 (Box 15, Folder 231 - 232)
  - Coleman, James P. [nomination for the Fifth Circuit Court of Appeals], 1965 (Box 16, Folder 233)
  - Committee for Fair Broadcasting of Controversial Issues, 1970 (Box 16, Folder 234)
  - Committee for Peaceful Alternatives, 1950 (Box 16, Folder 235)
  - Committee on Political Expression, 1980-1981 (Box 16, Folder 236)
  - Communications law, 1976-1979 (Box 16, Folder 237)
  - Communism
    See also: box 19, folders 289 - 290
    - Communist Control Act of 1954, Undated (Box 16, Folder 238)
    - Communist Party, Undated (Box 16, Folder 239)
    - Communist Party v. Subversive Activities Control Board, 1955, 1960 (Box 16, Folder 240)
  - Conference on Critical Legal Studies, 1978-1982, undated (Box 16, Folder 241)
  - Connecticut Civil Liberties Union
    - General, 1983-1984 (Box 16, Folder 242)
    - Connecticut Freedom of Information and Privacy Acts, 1977-1979 (Box 16, Folder 243 - 244)
    - Correspondence, 1970-1987 (Box 16, Folder 245 - 250)
    - Desegregation Committee, 1978 (Box 17, Folder 251)
    - Devlin case, 1964-1965 (Box 17, Folder 252)
    - Meeting minutes, 1963-1984 (Box 17, Folder 253 - 262)
    - Organization and development, 1956-1968 (Box 18, Folder 263 - 264)
    - Publications [news releases, Inside CCLU bulletins, newsletters], 1970-1984 (Box 18, Folder 265 - 267)
    - State Board of Directors meeting minutes, 1984-1985 (Box 18, Folder 268)
  - Connecticut Commission on the Status of Women
    See: box 46, folders 654 - 663
    See: box 47, folders 664 - 671
    See: box 48, folders 675 - 676
    See: box 49, folders 685 - 694
  - Connecticut Women's Educational and Legal Fund, 1976-1984 (Box 18, Folder 269 - 276)
  - Conscientious objectors, 1952, 1965-1967, undated (Box 18, Folder 277)
  - Conspiracy law, 1969-1972 (Box 19, Folder 278 - 280)
  - Corliss Lamont Foundation, 1972-1974, undated (Box 19, Folder 281)
  - Crime Control Acts, 1970 (Box 19, Folder 282)
  - Criminal code revision
    - House Resolution 10850, 1976 (Box 19, Folder 283)
    - Senate Bill 1437, 1977-1978 (Box 19, Folder 284 - 285)
  - Criminal Justice Reform Act of 1975 (S-1 Bill), 1975-1976 (Box 19, Folder 286 - 288)
  - Davis, Angela, 1970-1974 (Box 19, Folder 289 - 290)
  - Defamation, 1947-1951, 1968, 1978-1980, undated (Box 19, Folder 291 - 292)
  - Discrimination
    - Administration of justice, 1962 (Box 19, Folder 293)
    - Education
      See also: box 25, folders 361 - 364
      See also: box 57, folders 799 - 800
      See also: box 64, folders 883 - 884
    - Employment, 1948, 1963-1978, undated (Box 20, Folder 298 - 300)
    - Housing, 1951-1964 (Box 20, Folder 301)
    - State legislation, 1951-1957 (Box 20, Folder 302 - 303)
  - Do Not Enter: The Visa War Against Ideas [documentary film], 1984-1985 (Box 20, Folder 304)
  - Doe v. Ullman, 1958-1960 (Box 20, Folder 305)
  - Douglas, William O.
    See also: box 75, folder 23
    - General, 1975-1980, undated (Box 20, Folder 306 - 307)
    - Douglas anniversary convocation, 1973-1974 (Box 20, Folder 308 - 309)
    - Inquiry, 1981-1983, undated (Box 20, Folder 310 - 311)
    - Inquiry into the state of individual freedom, 1977-1978 (Box 21, Folder 312 - 313)
  - Due process, 1964-1965 (Box 21, Folder 314)
  - Durr, Clifford, 1975 (Box 21, Folder 315)
  - Economic interests [picketing, boycotts, etc.], 1967-1969, undated (Box 21, Folder 316)
  - Elections, 1946-1984 (Box 21, Folder 317 - 323)
  - Emergency Civil Liberties Committee, 1951-1987 (Box 22, Folder 324 - 331)
  - Equal protection -Legal doctrines, 1954-1971, undated (Box 22, Folder 332)
  - Equal Rights Amendment
    - General
      - 1970-1976 (Box 22, Folder 333 - 335)
      - 1977-1986 (Box 23, Folder 336 - 338)
    - Congress, 1970-1972, undated (Box 23, Folder 339 - 340)
    - Emerson's supporting statements, 1977-1983 (Box 23, Folder 341)
    - Emerson testimonies, speeches, 1974-1977 (Box 23, Folder 342 - 343)
    - Hearings, 1971, 1983, undated (Box 23, Folder 344)
    - Ratification
      - General
        - 1972-1973 (Box 23, Folder 345 - 346)
        - 1974-1982 (Box 24, Folder 347 - 349)
      - Extension, 1977-1979, undated (Box 24, Folder 350 - 351)
    - Rescission, 1976-1979 (Box 24, Folder 352)
  - Espionage, 1957-1985 (Box 24, Folder 353 - 355)
    See also: box 58, folders 825 - 826
  - Ethics in government, 1964-1976 (Box 24, Folder 356)
  - Federal anti-subversive legislation, 1957, 1966 (Box 24, Folder 357)
  - Federal Bureau of Investigation, 1947-1987, undated (Box 24, Folder 358 - 360)
  - Federal Civil Rights Acts, 1956, 1969, 1972-1976, undated (Box 25, Folder 361 - 364)
  - Federal Criminal Code, 1973-1974 (Box 25, Folder 365 - 366)
  - Federal legislative committees, 1952-1971 (Box 25, Folder 367 - 369)
  - Federal legislative investigating committee, Undated (Box 25, Folder 370)
  - Federalism, 1963-1977 (Box 25, Folder 371)
  - Field Foundation, 1959-1960, 1984-1985 (Box 25, Folder 372 - 374)
  - Flag desecration, 1966-1967 (Box 25, Folder 375)
  - Fortas memorial, 1982 (Box 25, Folder 376)
  - Fourteenth Amendment [materials relating to an article co-authored by Emerson entitled "Forgotten Remedy for the Voteless Negro" that appeared in the January 21, 1961, edition of The Nation ], 1960-1965 (Box 25, Folder 377 - 379)
  - Freedom and national security, 1949-1952 (Box 26, Folder 380)
  - Freedom of belief, 1952, 1971, undated (Box 26, Folder 381)
  - Freedom of expression and science, 1977-1980, undated (Box 26, Folder 382)
  - Freedom of information
    - Dissemination of scientific information, 1983 (Box 26, Folder 383)
    - Free trade in ideas, 1984, undated (Box 26, Folder 384)
    - Freedom of Information Act (FOIA)
      - General, 1978 (Box 26, Folder 385)
      - Cases, 1977, 1982 (Box 26, Folder 386)
      - CIA exemption, 1983-1985 (Box 26, Folder 387)
      - Sunshine laws, 1978-1981, undated (Box 26, Folder 388)
    - Right to know, 1972-1974, undated (Box 26, Folder 389 - 390)
  - Freedom of movement [passports, travel, visas, etc.], 1955-1958, 1966-1973, undated (Box 26, Folder 391 - 393)
  - Freedom of speech, 1958-1982 (Box 26, Folder 394 - 399)
  - Freedom of the press, 1971-1979 (Box 27, Folder 400 - 403)
  - Fund for Open Information and Accountability, 1980-1982 (Box 27, Folder 404)
  - Gelfan, Dr. Samuel, 1971-1974 (Box 27, Folder 405)
  - Giese v. U.S., 1978-1980 (Box 27, Folder 406 - 407)
  - Government secrecy, 1976-1984 (Box 27, Folder 408)
  - Greater New Haven Committee for a Sane Nuclear Policy, 1959-1967 (Box 27, Folder 409)
  - Griswold v. Connecticut
    - Clippings, 1965 (Box 27, Folder 410)
    - Correspondence, 1960-1967, 1985 (Box 27, Folder 411 - 412)
    - Harper, Fowler
      - Correspondence, 1964 (Box 28, Folder 413)
      - Legal materials, 1964 (Box 28, Folder 414)
    - Legal materials, 1964-1965, undated (Box 28, Folder 415)
    - Supreme Court opinions, 1965 (Box 28, Folder 416)